A Guide to the James Koller Papers 1974.0002
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
James Koller Papers
1959-1986
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1974.0002
7.5 Linear Feet
The collection consists of letters to James Koller from various friends and colleagues, including Philip Whalen, and original manuscripts and typescripts of Koller's poetry and novels.
Biography of
Born in 1936 in Oak Park, Illinois, Koller is an American poet, novelist, editor and publisher. Koller obtained his B.A. from North Central College in Naperville, Illinois, in 1958; he then moved to San Francisco where he became the editor of Coyote's Journal, and the publisher of Coyote Books. He later moved with the magazine to New Mexico, and then to Maine. Koller has authored twenty-seven collections of poetry and four novels, and was a National Endowment for the Arts fellowship recipient in both 1968 and 1973.
Scope and Contents
The collection primarily consists of letters to James Koller from various friends and colleagues (including Philip Whalen) and original manuscripts and typescripts of Koller's poetry and novels. The materials date from 1959-1986. Dan Cushman's novel Stay Away, Joe (New York: Viking Press, 1953 ) was originally included in the collection, attached to Bill Deemer's February 6, 1984 letter to Koller.
Organization
Series I: Correspondence (1959-1986)
Series II: Writings (1965-1976)
Series III: Photographs (1969-1979)
Arrangement
Series I: Correspondence has been arranged alphabetically according to the last name of each letter's author. Series II: Writings has been re-foldered to accommodate size, and arranged alphabetically according to the name of each piece. Photographs have been separated from their original letters or manuscripts and placed in envelopes in Series III, arranged alphabetically according to their description.
Acquisition Information
Theis collection was purchased in 1974.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Bibliography
Contemporary Authors Autobiography Series, Volume 5, Gale, 1987.
Who's Who In Writers, Editors & Poets, 1989-90, Highland Park: December Press, 1989.
Contemporary Poets, 6th edition, St. James Press, 1996.
Contemporary Authors Online. The Gale Group, 2000.
Albuquerque (inhabited place); Manuscripts (document genre); Brunswick (Me.); New Mexico (state); Maine (state); Twentieth century.; American poetry; Periodicals; San Francisco (inhabited place); Poetry -- Editing; California (state); Illinois (state); Typescripts; Correspondence; Photographs; Authors; Editors; Notes; Poems; Arnold, Bob.; Beltrametti, Franco.; Dorn, Edward; Koller, James; Coyote Books.; Deemer, Bill.; Clark, Tom; Kelly, Robert, 1935-; McClure, Michael; Kyger, Joanne; Taggart, John, 1942-; Whalen, Philip; Waldman, Anne, 1945-; Eigner, Larry, 1927-.; Ginsberg, Allen, 1926-1997; Enslin, Theodore; Hyner, Stefan; Snyder, Gary, 1930-; Hollo, Anselm; Creeley, Robert, 1926-2005; Kahn, Paul.; Waldman, Anne, 1945-
- Series I: Correspondence, undated, 1960-1986
  - Allen, Donald M., 1974-1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Arnold, Bob, 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Arnold, Bob, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Arnold, Bob, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Arnold, Bob, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Arnold, Bob, 1984 January - May (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Arnold, Bob, 1984 June - December (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Arnold, Bob, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Beltrametti, Franco, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Beltrametti, Franco, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Beltrametti, Franco, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Beltrametti, Franco, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Beltrametti, Franco, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Beltrametti, Franco, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Beltrametti, Franco, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Beltrametti, Franco, 1983-1986 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Beltrametti, Judy, 1974-1981 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Bersenbrugbe, Mei Mei, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Bertholf, Robert, 1972-1978 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Bertolino, James, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Blackburn, Joan, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Blackburn, Paul, 1966-1971 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Blue Cloud, Peter, 1976-1983 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Bly, Robert, [1973?] (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Boyce, Jack, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Brantigan, Richard, 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Bruchac, Joseph, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Butterick, George, 1974-1982 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Carroll, Paul, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Clark, Tom, 1969-1982 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Clarke, Jack, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Cody, Jim, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Collom, Jack, 1972-1975 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Crreley, Robert, 1966, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Deemer, Bill, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Deemer, Bill
    - "Glorious Signs of a Beautiful Person" original drawing, 1965 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - "Let me not to the marriage of true minds admit impediments" Broadside of sonnet for Deemer wedding, 1966 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Deemer, Bill, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Deemer, Bill, 1969-1973 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Deemer, Bill, 1974-1980 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Deemer, Bill, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Deemer, Bill, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Deemer, Bill, 1983-1985 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Deemer, Bill, undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Dorn, Edward, 1968-1980 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Duerden, Richard, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Eigner, Larry, 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Ekner, Reidor, 1980-1984 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Ekvall, Robert E., 1972-1975 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Enslin, Theodore, undated (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Enslin, Theodore, 1975-1985 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Eulart, Don, 1972-1975 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Faulwell, Dean, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Finkel, Donald, 1972-1978 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Finstein, Max, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Garland, Peter, 1972-1985 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Gifford, Barry, 1974-1977 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Ginsberg, Allen, 1966-1977 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Glover, Albert, 1972-1974 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Goodell, Larry, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Halper, Jon, 1976-1980 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Hamill, Sam, 1978-1980 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Hemensley, Kris, 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Hollo, Anselm, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Hoogstraten, Harry, 1972-1978 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Hoogstraten, Harry, 1979-1984 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Hyner, Stefan, 1978-1981 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - Hyner, Stefan, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - Hyner, Stefan, 1983-1985 (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - Isherwood, Justin, 1972-1980 (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Jaegar, Julia Newman, 1970-1974 (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - Johnstone, Paul, 1976-1979 (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - Kahn, Paul, 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - Kahn, Paul, 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - Kahn, Paul, 1979-1981 (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - Kahn, Paul, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Kahn, Paul, 1983-1985 (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Karr, Ted, 1972-1976 (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - Kelly, Robert, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - Kohler, Michael, 1977-1979 (Box 5, Folder 78)
  - Koller, James/Johnstone, Paul, 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 79)
  - Koller, James/Kyger, Joanne, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 80)
  - Koller, James/McClure, Michael, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 81)
  - Koller, James/Rosenthal, Irving, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 82)
  - Koller, James/Steve & Peter, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 83)
  - Kooler, James/Whalen, Philip, 1963-1964 (Box 5, Folder 84)
  - Kwong, Bill, 1972-1981 (Box 5, Folder 85)
  - Kyger, Joanne, 1966-1983 (Box 5, Folder 86)
  - Lawless, Gary, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - Lawless, Gary, 1980-1981 (Box 5, Folder 88)
  - Lewandowski, Steve, 1979-1980 (Box 6, Folder 89)
  - Longville, Tim, 1969-1980 (Box 6, Folder 90)
  - MacAdams, Lewis, 1977-1980 (Box 6, Folder 91)
  - MacDonald, Douglas, 1972-1975 (Box 6, Folder 92)
  - MacDonald, Douglas, 1976-1980 (Box 6, Folder 93)
  - Martin, John, 1970-1973 (Box 6, Folder 94)
  - Martin, John, 1974-1979 (Box 6, Folder 95)
  - Martin, John, 1980-1986 (Box 6, Folder 96)
  - Martin, Paul, 1975-1979 (Box 6, Folder 97)
  - McClure, Michael, 1960-1967 (Box 6, Folder 98)
  - McCord, Howard, 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 99)
  - McNaughton, Duncan, 1974-1980 (Box 6, Folder 100)
  - McNult, Tim, 1980-1983 (Box 6, Folder 101)
  - Miller, Steve, 1978-1979 (Box 6, Folder 102)
  - Millward, Pamela, 1975-1980 (Box 6, Folder 103)
  - Miodini, Cate, 1980-1982 (Box 6, Folder 104)
  - Mottram, Eric, 1972-1979 (Box 7, Folder 105)
  - Nemirow, Steve, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 106)
  - Propper, Dan, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 107)
  - Rathbu, Roberto, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 108)
  - Reyes, Carlos, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 109)
  - Rodefer, Stephen, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 110)
  - Rosenthal, Irving, 1959-1960 (Box 7, Folder 111)
  - Rothenberg, Jerome, 1970-1985 (Box 7, Folder 112)
  - Ruutila, Ecru, 1978-1980 (Box 7, Folder 113)
  - Sanfield, Steven, 1974-1978 (Box 7, Folder 114)
  - Shoemaker, Jack, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 115)
  - Snyder, Gary, 1966-1972 (Box 7, Folder 116)
  - Snyder, Gary, 1975-1983 (Box 7, Folder 117)
  - Skingass, David, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 118)
  - Steuding, Bob, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 119)
  - Sze, Arthur, 1981-1983 (Box 7, Folder 120)
  - Taggart, John, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 121)
  - Tarachon, Michael, 1980-1981 (Box 7, Folder 122)
  - Tarn, Nathaniel, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 123)
  - Urdang, Constance, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 124)
  - Van Aelstyn, Edward, 1970-1978 (Box 7, Folder 125)
  - Vas Dias, Robert, 1972-1982 (Box 7, Folder 126)
  - Vega, Janine Pommy, 1976-1978 (Box 7, Folder 127)
  - Vega, Janine Pommy, 1979-1982 (Box 7, Folder 128)
  - Vincent, Stephen, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 129)
  - Wah, Fred, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 130)
  - Waldman, Anne, 1969-1982 (Box 8, Folder 131)
  - Warsh, Lewis, 1968-1970 (Box 8, Folder 132)
  - Whalen, Philip, 1963-1966 (Box 8, Folder 133)
  - Whalen, Philip, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 134)
  - Whalen, Philip, 1968-1969 (Box 8, Folder 135)
  - Whalen, Philip, 1970-1972 (Box 8, Folder 136)
  - Whalen, Philip, 1974-1985 (Box 8, Folder 137)
  - Wilk, David, 1978-1982 (Box 8, Folder 138)
  - Wilson, Keith, 1971-1981 (Box 8, Folder 139)
  - Other Correspondence (A-Z, Unidentified), 1970-1985 (Box 8, Folder 140)
- Series II: Writings, 1965-1976
  - "The Blackberries were not Ripe", 1966 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - "Blue-Green A Mountain Lake", 1966 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Born at Night/In Red Trimmed Blue Shoes", 1966 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - California Poems, 1971 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - "Crows Fill the Trees", 1968 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - "Elisabeth, Elisabeth, Elisabeth Yellow Hair", 1967 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - "For Charles Hassler & Sally Jo Knowles", 1966 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - He Only Dreamed of Places Now", 1966 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Here I am Again", 1965 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - "How It Happened", 1965 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - "I Tried to Write You a Song", 1966 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - "I Went to See My True Love", 1966 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - "I'd Climb the Highest Mountain with You", 1966 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - If You Don't Like Me You Can Leave Me Alone, undated
    - Original TS with ms corrections (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Original TS with ms corrections (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Original TS with ms corrections--full ms (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Original TS and MS, "Notes for Movie & Novel" (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - "I'm Going Home", 1965 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - "Lightening Coming Home", 1968 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - "Mars the Ruler", 1968 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - "Moon, Moon, Moon", 1968 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - "On Her Knees", 1968 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Poems for the Blue Sky", 1976 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - "Radio Poem", 1965 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Shannon Who Was Lost Before, undated
    - Original TS (Box 10, Folder 25)
    - Original TS (Box 10, Folder 26)
    - Original TS with ms corrections (Box 10, Folder 27)
    - Original TS with ms corrections (Box 10, Folder 28)
    - Original TS with ms corrections [Draft 1] (Box 10, Folder 29)
    - Original TS with ms corrections [Draft 1] (Box 10, Folder 30)
    - Original TS with ms corrections [Draft 2] (Box 10, Folder 31)
    - Original TS with ms corretions [Draft 2] (Box 10, Folder 32)
    - Original TS with ms corrections [Draft 3] (Box 11, Folder 33)
    - Original TS with ms corrections [Draft 3] (Box 11, Folder 34)
    - Original Ts with ms corrections [Draft 4] (Box 11, Folder 35)
  - Skins/Poems 1959-1967, 1969 (Box 11, Folder 36)
  - Skins/Poems 1959-1967, 1969 (Box 11, Folder 37)
  - "So Early to Wake", 1966 (Box 11, Folder 38)
  - Songs of the Teton Sioux, undated (Box 11, Folder 39)
  - "Sleepy Naked Piss", 1968 (Box 11, Folder 40)
  - "Snow on Mt. St. Helena", 1967 (Box 11, Folder 41)
  - "Sorry Lady, the Train Just Left 10 Minutes Ago", 1966 (Box 11, Folder 42)
  - "That Fall, on Bicycle, at Dusk", 1966 (Box 11, Folder 43)
  - "Three Hawks, Low", 1968 (Box 11, Folder 44)
  - Two Hands/Poems 1959-1961, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 45)
    - Complete set of 26 offset plates, oversize, 1965 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - "Two Red Roses", 1968 (Box 11, Folder 46)
  - Untitled Scenario, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 47)
  - "We Came Out of That City", 1968 (Box 11, Folder 48)
  - "Well, If it Ain't Old Wolf Tit", 1965 (Box 11, Folder 49)
  - Wind/Fragments for a Beginning, undated (Box 11, Folder 50)
  - "Wish You Were Here", 1965 (Box 11, Folder 51)
- Series III: Photographs, undated, 1969-1979
  - "Bearhunters' Cave", undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - "Beowulf!", 1979 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - "Boys Peeking Thru Fence", 1978 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - "Bull & Matador", undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - "Esopus Rises", undated (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - "House", undated (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - "Junk Truck", 1969 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - "Junk Truck Negative", 1969 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - "Landscape", undated (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - "Little Girl", undated (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - "Man Reading Book", undated (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - "Man Wearing Suspenders", 1978 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - "Man With Pipe", undated (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - "Sailing Trophies", 1978 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Skins cover photograph, undated (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - "Sleeping Baby", undated (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - "Three Person Band", undated (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - "Two Girsl & Cat", undated (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - "Woman Holding Infant", undated (Box 12, Folder 19)